<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Awake Sampson, the Philistines are upon thee! or, A caution to England to take heed to her locks, least they being cut off by intrigues, she be made to grind at the mill of France ... by a lover of the true interest of his country.</title>
            <author>Lover of the true interest of his country.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4275A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11712881</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11712881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 9:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Awake Sampson, the Philistines are upon thee! or, A caution to England to take heed to her locks, least they being cut off by intrigues, she be made to grind at the mill of France ... by a lover of the true interest of his country.</title>
                  <author>Lover of the true interest of his country.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Bridge ..., and sold by E. Whitelock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Awake SAMPSON, THE PHILISTINES Are Upon Thee! OR, A CAUTION TO ENGLAND, To take heed to her <hi>LOCKS,</hi> leaſt they being Cut off by Intrigues, ſhe be made to Grind at the MILL of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being Preparatory to a more General Alarm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lover of the True Intereſt of his Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Bridge</hi> in <hi>Auſtin Friers,</hi> and ſold by <hi>E. Whitelock</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE following Diſcourſe being principally matter of fact, drawn from ſeveral Obſervations, made in the laſt Two Reigns, and ſince the late Revolution, with a ſhort Account of the Endeavours uſed to bring us under the <hi>French</hi> Government, from which we have been ſo oft Providentially delivered, I have the leſs occaſion to make any Apology for this ſhort Narrative, intended only as a preparatory to a more <hi>General Alarm,</hi> to awaken us out of that dangerous Lethargy many of us are fallen into.</p>
            <p>I have waved Perſonal Reflections, without any ſelf-prejudice to any body, becauſe that ſort of Writing is like throwing in Fuel, which inflames, inſtead of Water, to quench Fire; my deſire being nothing elſe but to promote our real, general <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt: That hath been and ſtill is, and ſhall for the future continue to be my Endeavour, whatever it coſt me, having hitherto conſulted no Difficulty in the Publick Service, tho expos'd to many audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Repulſes, yet have again rallied as a true <hi>Engliſhman.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <p>THE comparing our preſent condition, as it ſtands betwixt us and <hi>France,</hi> with <hi>Sampſon</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> may not, I hope, be thought improper, who altho he had ſeveral Warnings of their Deſign to deſtroy him; yet by his careleſneſs, truſt, and ſleeping in the Lap of her that was in the Intrigue with them, he was taken Captive by his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Tho we have had many Cautions, and ſignal Warnings of the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> yet (generally ſpeaking) we would ſcarce believe our ſelves in any danger; but tho the <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> in King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d's time, was afterwards endeavoured to be ſhamm'd, yet is it not now (with a Witneſs) made out by the laſt part of the ſaid Plot, <hi>viz.</hi> the adulterating the Coin.</p>
            <p>And altho we are now under a preſent aſtoniſhing acknowledgement of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in the late Preſervation of His Majeſties Royal Perſon, and preventing the effuſion of ſo much Bloud, as was intended, by this laſt horrid Conſpiracy, with the total deſtruction of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion; yet how inſenſible are too many perſons already growing, and ready to cool, as if they were reſolved not to ſee the Sun at Noon-Day, and conſent (as <hi>Sampſon</hi> in the Lap of <hi>Delilah</hi>) to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with utter darkneſs.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, there have been many Diſcourſes Printed about this Subject, by much abler Pens; but it being generally in ſuch Language, and ſo ſatyrical, that it doth no way anſwer the end ſo neceſſary for enlightning, on the one hand, and healing on the other hand: I ſhall therefore endeavour, as much as poſſible, to uſe ſuch cautions as may ſerve the ends propoſed; and ſhall offer that to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is matter of fact, with relation to <hi>France, (viz.)</hi> of the Deſign in both the late Reigns, to ſubvert the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and ſubject it to the Arbitrary Will and Pleaſure of the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>To effect which, the Trade of <hi>England</hi> was to be, in the firſt place, tranſplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>France,</hi> and it was ſo much effected, that in Twenty years time, it gained from us, near Four Millions <hi>per Annum,</hi> as is fully demonſtrated in a late Diſcourſe, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations of</hi> France <hi>upon</hi> England, by a Perſon who has made his particular Obſervations thereon in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>And though in Trade it ſelf its generally reported, that <hi>France</hi> (by way of Barter) got from <hi>England</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of a Million of Pounds <hi>Sterling per Annum,</hi> for ſeveral Years laſt paſt, which is only known by the Entries made in our Cuſtom-Houſe-Books; yet this (to thoſe that know the Intrigues of that People) may not be one half in value of the Goods imported from <hi>France.</hi> For that which comes in by Stealth (and of ſuch ſome Perſons are ſo fond, as to give double, if not treble the worth of it, only to have the name of <hi>French</hi>) may be as much in the Sum, if not more than what is truly and really Entered, which for the moſt part are bulky Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:4"/>
            <p>
               <q>And as our Loſs in the Trade with <hi>France</hi> is about Two Millions <hi>per Annum,</hi> by the Importation of their Commodities here; ſo its preſumed (on very good grounds) that the Exportation of our Wooll thither, unwrought, enriches <hi>France,</hi> much more than all the Importation of <hi>French</hi> Goods into <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Author did publiſh his Fears of that evil about 27 years ago, which were afterwards in the year 1677, renewed by the ſame hand in a Diſcourſe, Intituled, <hi>The Proverb croſſed;</hi> and alſo much enlarged by Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvel,</hi> which he Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed under the notion of a younger Brother in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to his elder Brother in <hi>England,</hi> occaſioned by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Act, Prohibiting the Importation of Cattel.</p>
            <p>And in the ſecond place, the whole frame of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, was to be ſubverted at once; and therefore the Plot in the year 1678, was ſo laid, and the adulterating the Coin was then deſigned to be the laſt part of the ſaid Plot; and had we took that caution given us timely, we had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented many of thoſe evils, which we have ſo ſenſibly ſince felt, and have yet cauſe to fear greater.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, ſince it hath pleaſed God (who alone hath done it) to diſcover thoſe ſecret Plots, and late Deſigns of the Enemies of our Peace not only of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as a Free Nation, but alſo the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion it ſelf; let us make that uſe of it, as becometh rational perſons.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Deſigns of our Enemies have been variouſly exerciſed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to deſtroy our Trade, to envade Property, to alter our Religion, and to Adulterate the Coin of the Nation; let us now conſider, being ſo long ago told of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of our Enemies, and not gratifie them, and ruine our ſelves</p>
            <p>The following Diſcourſe being moſtly nothing but matter of fact, it requires little, if any Apology at all.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Awake</hi> Sampſon, &amp;c. <hi>Or,</hi> A CAVEAT <hi>to England,</hi> not to be Trappann'd, by <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THAT the Revolution in 1688 (as juſt one Hundred years before) in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting our falling both into Popery and Slavery, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King's Tyranny, was then look'd upon by the Body of the Nation, to be the wonderful Providence of God, and next to a Miracle, That the then Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (now our King) with ſo ſmall an Army, to adventure at ſuch a ſeaſon of the Year, as the dead of Winter, and ſo long a Voyage, and to ſail by ſuch a ſtrong Fleet, almoſt in ſight, then in the <hi>Downs,</hi> and alſo ſuch a great and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd Army here in <hi>England,</hi> well paid, and the <hi>French</hi> ready to aſſiſt upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for I was inform'd that very evening that the News came of the late King's leaving <hi>Salisbury,</hi> by a perſon privy to that King's Deſign, that there were betwixt <hi>Calis</hi> and <hi>Bullen,</hi> about thirty thouſand <hi>French</hi> Soldiers, deſign'd to Embark for <hi>England;</hi> and <hi>Dover</hi>-Caſtle was to protect ſuch as ſhould Land there; and <hi>Shereneſs</hi> and <hi>Tilbury</hi> Fort were to receive others to block up <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Chatham;</hi> and had not the Lord by the ſame Providence defeated their Deſigns, partly by the Diviſions of the late King's Council, (as in the caſe of <hi>Abſolon</hi>) and by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that the <hi>French</hi> King took thereupon, (as in another Diſcourſe enlarged) which had it not been thus, but that the <hi>French</hi> Army had Landed, and any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of the King's Army ſtood by him, what Confuſion muſt this poor Nation have been in, <hi>viz. England</hi> before now might have had the ſame fate of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> hath deſtroyed, or are in poſſeſſion, and thereby the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion at once, had been endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered, if not deſtroyed, and been ſubject to the <hi>French</hi> King's Tyranny.</p>
            <p>And that ſome of thoſe perſons that then invited and encouraged the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> now our King, not only to expoſe his Royal Perſon, in coming hither from <hi>Holland,</hi> but alſo, when come, in purſuance of the ſaid Invitation, deſired his acceptation of the Government, and put the Sword in his hands; why ſuch perſons in ſo ſhort a time, ſhould oppoſe what they had then juſt before done, I will not preſume to be judge of; but this I may ſay, what was then matter of fact, <hi>viz.</hi> the hindring a ſpeedy Reduction of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which for that reaſon, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the ſpilling of ſo much Bloud, and expending ſo vaſt a Treaſure, to the undoing ſeveral Thouſands thereby: And we cannot but own alſo a Divine Hand in that Reduction; when that whole Kingdom, except <hi>Londonderry,</hi> and ſome few Forts, were then in the hands of the <hi>French;</hi> for I look upon the late King to be but his Deputy, if ſo much: And why <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> ſhould ſo ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict themſelves in ſo ſhort a time, is ſtrange, and oppoſe that Deliverance from the <hi>French</hi> Tyranny, which they well knew, was all along deſign'd in both the late Reigns, and more plainly appearing by <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters, and ſeveral other Tranſactions publickly detected ſince</p>
            <p>And that Freemen ſhould ſo earneſtly long to be in Bondage and Slavery to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48293:5"/>that moſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> King, may ſeem ſtrange, who hath ſo much delighted in Bloud, and not only deſtroyed (without cauſe) ſo many Thouſand Subjects of other Princes, but alſo of thoſe whom he hath himſelf owned to be his moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious and Loyal Subjects, which may appear in a Letter to the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> dated the Sixth of <hi>September,</hi> 1666.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The <hi>French</hi> King's Letter to the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BROTHER, I would not have Diſcourſed the matter you wrote to me about on the behalf of my Subjects of the pretended <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> with any other Prince beſides your ſelf, but to ſhew you the particular eſteem I have for you.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall begin with telling you, that ſome perſons, diſaffected to my ſervice, have ſpread Seditious Pamphlets among Strangers, as if the Acts and Edicts that were paſſed in favour of my ſaid Subjects of the pretended <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> by the Kings my Predeceſſors, and confirmed by my Self, were not kept and executed in my Dominions, which would have been contrary to my intentions. For I take care that they be maintained in all the Priviledges which have been Granted them, and be as kindly uſed as my other Subjects; to this I am engaged both by my Royal Word, and in acknowledgment of the proofs they have given me of their Loyalty, during the late Troubles, in which they took up Arms for my Service, and did vigorouſly oppoſe, and ſucceſsfully overthrow the ill deſigns which a Rebellious Party were contriving within my own Dominions, againſt my Authority Royal.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>What his Hypocriſie was then, appears in his Edict, <hi>October</hi> 1685. <hi>viz.</hi> when he thought he was ready to put in execution his Deſign, and had the late King <hi>James</hi> to join with him to carry it on, in which Edict he expoſes his Granfather <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> who had ſo nobly declared himſelf in his Edict of <hi>Nants, April</hi> 1598. he begins thus,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Edict of <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King's Grandfather.</head>
                  <p>NOW it hath pleaſed God to give us a beginning of enjoying ſome reſt, we think we cannot employ our ſelves better, than to apply to that which may tend to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Glory of his Holy Name, and to provide that he may be adored, and prayed to by all our Subjects, and if it hath not yet pleaſed him to permit it to be in one and the ſame form of Religion, that it may at leaſt be in one and the ſame intention, and with ſuch Rules, that may prevent amongſt them all Troubles and Tumults; and that we and this Kingdom, may always conſerve the Glorious Title of <hi>Moſt Chriſtian;</hi> and by the ſame means, take away the cauſe of Miſchief and Trouble, which may happen from the Actions of Religion, which of all others, are moſt prevalent and penetrating; for this cauſe, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging this Affair to be of the greateſt Importance, and worthy of the beſt conſideration; after having conſidered the complaints of our <hi>Catholick</hi> Subjects; and having alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our Subjects of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> to aſſemble themſelves by Deputies for framing their Complaints, and making a Collection of all their Remonſtrances: Hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore conferred divers times with them, we have upon the whole, judged it neceſſary, to give to all our ſaid Subjects, one general Law, clear, plain and abſolute, by which they ſhall be regulated in all differences which have heretofore riſen among them, or may riſe hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48293:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>having had no other reguard in this deliberation, than ſolely the zeal we have to the Service of God; praying that he would henceforward grant to all our Subjects a durable and eſtabliſhed Peace; And we Implore and Expect from his Divine Bounty, the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Favour he hath always beſtowed upon this Kingdom from our Birth, and that he would give our ſaid Subjects the Grace to underſtand; That in obſervation of this our Ordinance, conſiſteth (next to their Duty towards God and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s) the principal foundation of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, Concord, Tranquility, Reſt, and the re-eſtabliſhment of this State in its firſt Splendour, Opulency and Strength; As on Our part We promiſe, that all the parts of it ſhall be exactly obſerved, without ſuffering any contravention; And for theſe cauſes, having with the Advice of the Princes of our Bloud, other Princes and Offieers of our Crown, and other Great and Eminent Perſons of our Council of State, well and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently weighed and conſidered all this Affair, we have by this Edict or Statute, perpetual and irrevocable, ſaid, declared and ordained, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>That after the ſaid Edict of <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> was ſo long quietly enjoyed by the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who continued always Loyal to their Prince, and as the preſent <hi>French</hi> King confeſſeth in his Letter to the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> had been ſo ſerviceable to him when he was in danger of his Crown, and that they were ſo greatly inſtrumental in ſettling him upon the Throne, that yet for that reaſon they ſhould be deſtroyed, is a ſtrange return of Gratitude; and if it be ſo, that he hath been ſo falſe and baſe to his own Loyal Subjects, it is no marvel that he hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with others, and true to none, (if not conſiſtent with his Ambition) let their obligations be never ſo great.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, it's incredible to think, that any <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to his Greatneſs, by creating objections againſt the preſent Government, and with ſo much induſtry, magnifie and ſpread them abroad, in order to inſtill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding Principles in honeſt, well-meaning mens Minds, than which nothing can poſſibly tend more to our own ruine, and promoting the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt. Nor can I ſee with what peace of Conſcience, ſuch Men can deſire that Miſery to befal <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> yea, even thoſe very perſons that have had particular obligations, tho never ſo great, to the late King <hi>James,</hi> eſpecially if ſome of his actions be duly conſidered, even ſuch as were tranſacted before his Abdication, as well as ſo lately attempted, which being matter of fact, carries its own evidence; for proof of which take the following account, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I remember at the latter end of the year 1687, when he had given a Commiſſion to inſpect what Fines had been Levied on the Diſſenters, and not paid into the Exchequer, (which was deſign'd, and afterwards appeared, not for any good to them, but to ſet <hi>Proteſtants</hi> one againſt another, to make way for the <hi>Papiſts</hi>) amongſt ſeveral illegal practices, there was one more notorious than others, (I ſpeak my own knowledge, being in that Commiſſion, and hearing the examination of the caſe) That a Juſtice of Peace in <hi>Middleſex,</hi> had cauſed the value of two hundred Pounds in Houſhold-Goods to be ſeized upon from a Diſſenter, yea his Childrens Cloths, and a Chimney-Piece to make it up, for ſeveral Meetings, (I could name both the Juſtice and the Diſſenter, if it were neceſſary) which Goods were all carried to the Juſtices Stables, and there divided without any Appraiſment, and reſtoring the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius back to the Owner; and ſo it fell out, one of the Commiſſioners, who had a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48293:6"/>great Intereſt in King <hi>James,</hi> did the next day inform him of the whole matter, who upon hearing thereof, ſeemed to be affected with the matter, inſomuch that I expected nothing leſs than a reſtoration; but the contrary fell out, for when we had ſummoned the Juſtice to anſwer the Charge, which was ſome Weeks e'r he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, he did not deny the fact, but produc'd a Witneſs that it was done by the ſaid King's particular order when he was Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What greater Hypocriſie could there be? and how much like his Brother in <hi>France</hi> before mentioned, to which may be added ſome other inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> One was in anſwer to an Addreſs, wherein he ſolemnly proteſted his averſion to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; and in another he called God to Witneſs, how much Perſecution was againſt his Judgment; and to a third Addreſs, he ſaid he had well conſidered the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> and wondred at his Brother the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Proceedings, how injurious they were to Trade; and added, That he <hi>would give them leave to Chalk his Back as a Fool, if he ſhould follow their ſteps;</hi> and to add a fourth, Printed on the Addreſs of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> he appealed to Mr. <hi>Pen,</hi> how for many years he knew him averſe to Perſecution, which calls to mind, a Paſſage I heard from the then Dutcheſs of <hi>York</hi>'s Secretary, in the year 1682, that he had often heard the Duke ſay, that to pleaſe ſome Diſſenters, eſpecially Mr. <hi>Ion,</hi> and other <hi>Quakers,</hi> he declared he was troubled at their Suffering, but afterwards laugh'd at them; beſides all which, many cannot but know, that moſt of the Severities uſed in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time, were influenced by the ſaid King <hi>James,</hi> as in the inſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the Juſtice of Peace, on purpoſe to put the Church of <hi>England</hi> to proſecute the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Diſſenters (when the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were quiet) to make way to promote <hi>Popery;</hi> and to conclude, his cauſing ſo many Worthy and Eminent Men, (averſe to <hi>Popery</hi>) to looſe their Lives, on purpoſe to deter others; and therefore its plain, what we may expect from Men of ſuch Principles, let their pretences be never ſo fair, which is already too notorious in the practice of the <hi>French</hi> King, and in part, began by the ſaid King <hi>James,</hi> in the laſt mentioned actions; and how near we were under the ſame kind of the <hi>French</hi> Government, by the late King's actions; and ſo long deſign'd by both the ſaid Kings, not only appearing in <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before mentioned, but in all their proceedings purſuant thereunto, which for <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> to promote, is monſtrous, and never to be pitied. I would upon this occaſion, and the late Deſign of the <hi>French,</hi> only incert the fact of <hi>Grandaval,</hi> who was Executed in <hi>Flanders</hi> the 13th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1692. for the ſame Deſign againſt His Majeſties Royal Perſon at that time; the Relation is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Some of the Miniſters in the higheſt Employments, and of the greateſt Credit in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> having formed a Deſign to aſſaſſinate His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> they made uſe of the ſaid <hi>Grandval,</hi> as their Inſtrument, to manage the Enterprize, to find out fit perſons to be employ'd in it; to engage them by promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of great rewards, as alſo to be aiding and aſſiſting in his own perſon.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Grandval</hi> being inform'd, that one <hi>Anthony du Mont</hi> had already been engaged in this deſign, in the Life time of the late Marquis <hi>de Louvois,</hi> he propoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to him again, to execute the ſame by order of the Marquis of <hi>Barbeſiaux,</hi> and ſome others. Whereupon ſeveral Projects were drawn up, and reſolution was taken to bring it to effect the Cauupaign 1691: but the Providence of God diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them; yet notwithſtanding they did not let fall the Proſecution of this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48293:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Deſign; but <hi>Grandval</hi> was employ'd frequently to write to <hi>Du Mont</hi> (who was retired to <hi>Hanover</hi>) to ſtir him up to another attempt, the Campaign of 1692, which at laſt they agreed upon.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Loofdate</hi> coming to <hi>Paris</hi> about that time, <hi>Grandval</hi> making an acquaintance with him, diſcovered to him the ſaid Deſign, which <hi>Loofdate</hi> ſhewing a willingneſs to be concern'd in, but ſoon after gave notice of it, by Letters, to his Relations in <hi>Holland,</hi> that they might inform his Majeſty; and the like Diſcovery was made by <hi>Du Mont</hi> to his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Zell,</hi> who acquainted His Majeſty with it about the ſame time that he received the other account.</p>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Grandval</hi> having appointed <hi>Du Mont</hi> a Rendevouz at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>den</hi> in the Country of <hi>Raveſtryn,</hi> he ſet out from <hi>Paris</hi> in company of <hi>Loofdate,</hi> paſſing thro <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> where he communicated his Deſign to one <hi>John d' Amours,</hi> who was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a Domeſtick Servant to <hi>Loofdate</hi>'s Father. From thence they went to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Eyndhoven,</hi> where <hi>Grandval</hi> was ſeized, and <hi>Bois le d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Loofdate</hi> upon Examination made out clearly all the circumſtances of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; and ſaid <hi>Grandval</hi> told him, <hi>That the King of</hi> Great Britain <hi>was looked upon as the only obſtacle to the</hi> French <hi>King's Deſigns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John d' Amours</hi> being Examined next, Depos'd, that <hi>Grandval</hi> told him at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> he had a great buſineſs to do, which had miſcarried the laſt year; and they two fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Diſcourſe about His Majeſty, <hi>John d' Amours</hi> asked <hi>Grandval,</hi> if he had any thing to ſay to the King, <hi>Yes,</hi> anſwered he, <hi>To break his Neck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Du Mont</hi> being Examined, owned the fact in all its circumſtances, adding ſeveral other particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> that Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi> (the <hi>French</hi> King's old Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine) was acquainted with the Deſign: and that if he <hi>(Grandval)</hi> ſucceeded in the buſineſs, he ſhould have an ample Recompence, even to be a Duke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grandval</hi> himſelf was Examined, and perceiving that the matter was Diſcovered, and that his own Letter could be produced to convict him, he freely confeſſed all the circumſtances of the Deſign, without ſo much as naming the Rack to him, either before or after Sentence. <hi>Grandval</hi> declared that he acted in this Damned Deſign, wholly in obedience to the Orders he had received from Monſieur <hi>Larbeſieux,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Chanlais,</hi> Miniſters of State to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>Barbeſieux</hi> promiſed <hi>Grandval</hi> an Annual Revenue of 20000 Livres, and to make him Knight of the Order of St. <hi>Lazarus,</hi> in caſe the deſign took effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grandval, Loofdate</hi> and Colonel <hi>Parker,</hi> went to <hi>St. Germain</hi> on the 16th of <hi>April</hi> 1692, to ſpeak with the late King <hi>James</hi> about the ſaid Deſign, who had knowledge of it. They all had Audience of the ſaid King, the late Queen being preſent. King <hi>James</hi> told <hi>Grandval,</hi> that <hi>Parker</hi> had given him an an account of the Buſineſs, and ſai, <hi>That if he and the other Officers would do him that Service, they ſhould never want.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grandval</hi> owned himſelf Guilty of the Deſign, and ſaid, <hi>He deſerved Death,</hi> and that, <hi>He had an Original Paper under Monſieur</hi> Barbeſieux's <hi>own hand to juſtifie himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>This Relation is ſo neceſſary at this time to be mentioned, becauſe it agrees with our late diſcovered Plot, and Anſwers all the Objections produced by the <hi>French</hi> Advocates. This Conſpiracy was carried on at that time when the late King <hi>James</hi> was preparing to Invade <hi>England</hi> that very Summer, 1692 And to this I ſhall crave leave to add an Abſtract of what was not long ſince Publiſhed, which was the Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48293:7"/>of a Gentleman of very good Note, who had ſeen moſt of the Tranſactions at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> from 90 to 94, who reported,</p>
            <q>
               <p>In the Year 92 the late King had great hopes to be reſtored with Triumph, and fed himſelf with the thought of being an abſolute Monarch, having about that time received great encouragement, as well from the Pope as from the <hi>French</hi> King, which made him look above the reach of his late Subjects, (as he thought) and to reject all the Lord <hi>Preſton</hi>'s Undertakings, and the reſt concerned in that Intrigue; which was like to have coſt the Lord <hi>Preſton</hi> his Life, and for which he had no Thanks; but on the contrary, was deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed for meddling; the late King proteſting then, <hi>That he had rather never ſee</hi> England, (and it's hoped never ſhall) <hi>then Come To, or Capitulate with his Subjects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:</hi> But he ſoon alter'd his Reſolutions, ſeeing Affairs abroad thwart his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and meeting with ſuch unexpected Diſappointments, which abated much of the thoughts he retain'd but a little before; ſo that of a ſudden Motion, he with great impatience, conſulted ſome of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Council, telling them, that he was reſolved to Treat with his late Subjects, and give them any Conditions rather than ſtand out any longer; concluding, that nothing would more conduce to his Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, than to reconcile himſelf to his late Subjects.</p>
               <p>In order thereto an Expreſs was ſent to <hi>England,</hi> with Inſtructions to the Lord <hi>Midleton,</hi> and ſome others, to Treat with the People, and to know their Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by feeling how their Pulſes beat, and accordingly to proceed; which the Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> did, and drew a Declaration, anſwerable to the deſires of the Churchmen of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and ſome other Heads of both the Kingdoms. After ſome Debates, the Lord <hi>Midleton</hi> went away for <hi>France,</hi> and arrived at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> the beginning of <hi>March</hi> 1692, (towards the beginning of the year 93.) produced the Declaration, which admitted of high Debates, and long Arguments <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> as their ſeveral ſeparate Intereſts, moved the Miniſters of St. <hi>Germains.</hi> But the Lord <hi>Melford</hi> ſtarted ſeveral Caſes of Conſcience, againſt the late King's ſigning the ſaid Declaration, inſomuch that to be ſatisfied therein, and to remove all ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Conſcience, the late King conſulted the Colledge of <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Colledge likewiſe. The Faculty of <hi>Sorbon</hi> declared againſt the ſaid Declaration, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Colledge for it. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Colledge gave theſe Reaſons, That the King was in Exile, baniſhed his Kingdom by his own Children, and Subjects, for his Religion; that as the Caſe ſtood with him, there was no remedy for his Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration left him, but to comply with his Subjects, and to ſign any Inſtrument what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, for to prevail with them to accept of him home again; and whatever he ſhould ſign while in Exile, and under Tribulation abroad, he ſhould not in Conſcience, be obliged to perform after his Reſtoration, as exacted from him <hi>per</hi> force in diſtreſs, which renders all conditions and agreements of that kind, neither obligatory, nor binding, any longer than a fair opportunity ſhould offer to break them; (and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he would but imitate his Brother <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> who took the Covenant in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after his Reſtoration, burnt it at <hi>London</hi> by the hands of the Common Hangman.) The Faculty of <hi>Sorbon</hi> declared againſt this kind of <hi>Machiavilian</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and againſt the Declaration too: Yet notwithſtanding, the late King did ſign the ſaid Declaration, on the conſideration aforeſaid. But the Lord <hi>Melford</hi> and the Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> fell out, and are to this day irreconcileable.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Declaration ſo ſigned by the late King, was ordered to be ſent into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48293:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be read there at the Head of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Troops, but was to them the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome and unacceptable Meſſage that ever they met withal, or that the late King could ſend them, finding by the ſaid Declaration that they loſt themſelves both at home and abroad by the late King; which cauſed ſuch a conſternation in the Camp, that the Soldiers (who would be glad of any occaſion to quit the Service, and to return home) openly mutined, having ſtarted the Queſtion, <hi>That now being Deſerted by King</hi> James, <hi>why ſhould they not go over to King</hi> William, <hi>and accept of Conditions?</hi> But the Queſtion was carried in the Negative; and an Expreſs ſent immediately to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> to let the late King know the Diſcontent among the Soldiers, and the Diſorders in the Camp, occaſion'd by the ſaid Declaration.</p>
               <p>Here King <hi>James</hi> comes to himſelf again, and after his old cuſtom of doing and undoing, gets another Declaration drawn, ſigns the ſame, to null the former, and ſends away two Gentlemen, and two Clergy-men of note, with this new Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for <hi>Flanders,</hi> to pacifie the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and to give them content; which for ſome days gave them ſatisfaction; but not ſo much as to harbour a good Thought of the late King, believing that if ever he ſhould be reſtored, they would be all loſt though his unconſtancy; and that by repoſing their Truſt in him, they confided in a rotten Reed: But however, they were appeaſed for that time.</p>
               <p>Here the late King, forgetting his laſt Declaration and Proteſtation to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> ſends the firſt Declaration for <hi>England</hi> without any amendment, or taking any notice of the laſt Declaration to the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> but with the former Exception againſt them, he lets it paſs for <hi>England;</hi> here (as they ſay abroad) it was publiſhed the 19th of <hi>May</hi> 1693; but ſeveral not believing the ſame to be the late King's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, but the product of ſome other Invention to amuſe the People, ſeem'd diſguſted at it, and would give it no Credit: But that the People may be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the ſaid Declaration, notice was ſent to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> what the People ſaid about it; and immediately to remove all doubts touching the ſame, the late King cauſed it to be put in the <hi>Paris Gazette;</hi> where (to his great diſhonour and diſadvantage) it was Publiſhed by Authority; which gave content in <hi>England,</hi> and great diſcontent to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, who were in great diſorder about it; but the <hi>French</hi> King promiſed to ſee them righted, who are weary of King <hi>James</hi> (except ſome Officers that cannot live ſo well at home as in their ſtation abroad) and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to quit the Service upon any reaſonable Conditions whatſoever, eſpecially the common Soldiers, who are extraordinary poor and diſſatisfied, would give any thing to be at home; and the conſtant Deſertion confirms it.</p>
               <p>The Nobility and Gentry of <hi>France,</hi> finding a Declaration of King <hi>James</hi> in the <hi>Paris Gazette,</hi> were ſurpriſed at it, and ſeeing him deſert the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, did look upon it as great inconſtancy of reſolution, which in truth remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Intereſt and Affection of the Clergy and Nobility of <hi>France</hi> from him, who, before that Publication, were all reſolved for him, and to promote his Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to their power; but ſince are grown cold upon the matter.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And is it not ſtrange, after ſuch a diſcovery of the Temper, and Principles of ſuch a Prince, now preſent with ſuch a Monſter in <hi>France,</hi> whoſe influences over him will ever be more powerful than his Brothers, even at their firſt Arrival in the year 1660? I ſay again, is it not ſtrange that <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> yea, thoſe very perſons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48293:8"/>that were greatly inſtrumental in the ſaid Revolution, and put the Sword into our King's hand, and whilſt he is uſing it, with the frequent hazard of his own Life, to ſave ours, and to free us from Popery and Slavery, that ſuch perſons ſhould caſt away all ſenſe of Mercy and Freedom, and long to be under Bondage to that moſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian King;</hi> (juſt as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even without ſuch occaſions as they had of old, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go back again to <hi>Egypt</hi>) and thus expoſing not only themſelves at preſent, to be a ſcorn and reproach to all the World, but alſo by it to be inſtrumental in enſlaving their own Poſterity, ſo much degenerating from the Ancient and Generous Principles of rational <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> even long before the word <hi>Proteſtant</hi> was ever known, as appears by the Act of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> III. time, beſides many others in the ſucceeding Reigns, by which <hi>England</hi> now enjoys thoſe excellent Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, even beyond any Nation whatſoever; and ſhall this Age be ſo fooliſh, as to be willing to loſe all, and ſubject it ſelf to one of the greateſt inhumane Tyrants in the World; Oh! that it may not be once named, that <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> ſhould ſo much degenerate; but let us reaſſume that Antient Spirit, and improve the opportunity of regaining our Honour, Peace and Liberty, purſuant to the King's Speech late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made to his Parliament, <hi>viz. That theſe Nations might be Settled, and the Peace of</hi> Europe <hi>made up;</hi> which Peace cannot well be made, nor long kept, but by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that aſpiring Prince (the <hi>French</hi> King) low, that hath occaſion'd ſo much bloud inhumanely to be ſpilt, for his Ambition and Pride, as well as of making ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Countrys deſolate; and therefore he that hath not only been ſo Tyrannical, but alſo Treacherous and Falſe to his Word and Oath, can never be truſted by any new Contracts, as the Emperor of <hi>Germany</hi> and King of <hi>Spain</hi> have ſo lately ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; and therefore nothing but a Power above him, can bring him to any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Terms to keep within bounds; for ſhould a Peace be concluded at ſuch a ſeaſon as this, I do foreſee, who have made it my buſineſs to obſerve the Intrigues of that King, that ſuch a Peace would end in our Ruine, as is very well obſerved by another hand in theſe words,</p>
            <q>'Tis true indeed, that Peace is the greateſt of National Felicities, and ought to be our moſt deſirable Bleſſing, eſpecially if we look back to that effuſion of bloud, and expence of Treaſure has already been made, and therefore to ſound the Trumpet for the encouragement of War, muſt be ſomewhat ungrateful in our ears: However, when thoſe two moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Motives <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> lay that unavoydable neceſſity upon us, That it's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible we can ſheath our Swords with any thing leſs, than giving up our Necks to a moſt certain Slavery; <hi>War</hi> and only <hi>War</hi> is our common ſecurity, Peace made up with an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, whoſe Power is too ſtrong, and Fidelity too weak, is only a Web-lawn to break through at pleaſure; and a reconciliation of Friendſhip with ſuch a Prince, is the only means to impower him to be a more dangerous, becauſe then a more ſurpriſing Enemy. Should <hi>France</hi> in her preſent height of Greatneſs, give a ceſſation to Hoſtility; 'tis certain, ſhe can never give a ceſſation to her Ambition; and 'tis as certain, that War is only rak'd up, not quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when the Coles of Ambition are ſtill glowing, that at any convenient Rupture, may ſit it freſh a blazing to that Aſpirer, that ſo viſibly aims at <hi>Univerſal Monarchy.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>Peace</hi> can be no more than Diſguiſe and Stratagem, the <hi>Snake in the Graſs</hi> is but too notoriouſly to be ſuſpected under ſo foler, how ſeemingly fair Bed of Flowers. In ſhort, in any preſent accommodation with <hi>France,</hi> her holding her hand, will be no other than to enable her to make a ſtronger Blow.</q>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48293:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>So that if we conſult our real Intereſt as <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> we ought to promote it; for future ſucceſs ſhould encourage us, eſpecially when we reflect upon the King's ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Campaign the laſt Year, when he gave ſo great a Check to the <hi>French</hi> King's Pride at the re-taling of <hi>Namur;</hi> and that the <hi>Venetians</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> that had ſo long ſtood out, come to acknowledge our King's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, let us not now loſe Ground again; for if we will but obſerve the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Providences of God to this Nation, we muſt needs own, it hath been ſtill kept almoſt by Miracles.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider ſome of our late Deliverances, and particularly that in the year 1692 (compar'd with that lately diſcoverd) and a little reflect thereon, and call to mind how near we were then to deſtruction, and knew it not, and what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God was at that time, it may cauſe us to ſtand amazed; for I had ſome private hints at that time, and wrote them to a Friend of mine, attending the King in <hi>Flanders,</hi> which Perſon had been juſt then preſerved from being drowned. An Abſtract of which Letter I ſhall Tranſcribe,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>London, <date>25th April <hi>1692.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I am glad to hear of your great Deliverance ſince you Landed on that ſide, but ſorry I have occaſion to tell you what my fears are, <hi>viz.</hi> that if the Lord be not as wonderful at this time in the preſervation of that Liberty he was pleaſed to work for us at His Majeſties firſt arrival from <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>1688;</hi> we are very like to go back again to that Bondage we were then delivered from; for the daily Collections furniſheth me with freſh occaſions of mourning; and but yeſterday I was caution'd not to expoſe my ſelf in that Poſt I have ſtood ſo long in, <hi>viz</hi> by oppoſing the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, for that the late King <hi>James</hi> would be here in a Month, and little oppoſition be made againſt him; having a ſecurity of a quiet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; and many reaſons were then given to induce me to believe it, which I ſhall, for other reaſons, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omit naming them; and if the Wind continue long as it is, and that the <hi>French</hi> Fleet are joined, they may come and do what they pleaſe, becauſe our Fleet are in no condition to oppoſe them, they being kept ſo long to Rendevouz in the <hi>Nore;</hi> when it was urged long before to Rendevouz at <hi>Spithead.</hi> I was in hopes that the King was ready to come back, but tho diſpairing of that, am now informed that he will be in the Fleet to animate the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer/>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Poſtſcript.</hi> Before Sealing, the Wind ſhifting, hath blowed away ſome of my fears.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>It was a great and wonderful Providence it was not effected; that had not the Wind ſhifted at that time, and prevented the <hi>French</hi> Fleet from coming upon us, they might have ſoon deſtroyed that Squadron then off the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and have Landed there and at <hi>Portſmouth;</hi> but as before hinted, the Wind ſhifting, the <hi>French</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations proved, not only abortive, but very deſtructive to them at that time.</p>
            <p>And it muſt be owned to be a Divine Hand at that time, in the very Wind, (as now lately upon this laſt Deſign of <hi>France</hi>) for as the <hi>Thoulon</hi> Squadron being ſtopt from coming, as was deſign'd, into the Channel, and when we were inform'd of their Deſign to Invade us, that then the Wind ſerved juſt ſo long, as to carry our Fleet from the <hi>Nore</hi> to the <hi>Downs,</hi> and then immediately in having it ſhift till the <hi>Dutch</hi> joined us; ſo that <hi>England</hi> may ſay of the Wind, as <hi>Deborah</hi> of old did of the Stars, who <hi>in their order fought for</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48293:9"/>
            <p>Let it be remembred, that the Wind at that time held Weſt and South-Weſt about 5 Weeks, was an apparent Providence to this Nation; and if we will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any thing of that Nature, we may conclude by the ſame Providence, what a Noble Peer of this Nation ſaid ſome years ago, upon a Defeat of ſome Rebels in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and diſcovery of a Plot in <hi>Lancaſhire, That God would deliver us whether we would or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Enemies Preparations proved then not only abortive, but an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was offered to gain a great Victory upon them; and had it been purſued, <hi>France</hi> (to ſpeak humanely) had in a great meaſure been ruined; for I was credibly inform'd by a Relation of mine, who was in the Engagement, and after the Fight did burn two great Ships of War at <hi>La Hogue,</hi> who obſerved, that had there been a few Men Landed, the <hi>French</hi> had fled when none purſued; their temerity of the one hand, and oppreſſion on the other, would have render'd them uncapable or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to defend their Country; the two powerful Motives that render'd the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution among us in 1688 ſo feaſible and eaſie. I ſpeak not at random, but on good Grounds, from the Information I then received a little before the ſaid Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by a perſon that had been in <hi>France</hi> about that time, who inform'd me, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho the Policy of the <hi>French</hi> King were ſuch, as that his Maritime and Frontier Towns were not ſo much oppreſs'd, yet moſt of the Inland Provinces were ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populated and impoveriſhed, that there were not Men left to Till the Ground, nor Dreſs the Vines, as afterwards was more plainly demonſtrated; and were we once unanimous, we might ſtrike Terrour into the mind of that haughty Monarch of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant what ſly Inſinuations have been uſed to undermine our preſent Government, by telling us by way of objection, <hi>viz. How the Authors of the</hi> Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian, <hi>and</hi> Piedmont <hi>Perſecution, and the</hi> Spaniſh Inquiſition <hi>ſhould eſtabliſh the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>Belief amongſt us?</hi> I would anſwer, That the preſent War, in which we are engaged with the Emperor, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> is not upon the account of Religion, but upon Property and Civil Rights in thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who oppoſed the <hi>French</hi> King's Ambition; and the War with the Emperor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was long before our Revolution. And therefore it was a very great Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to us in <hi>England,</hi> as well as other <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Countrys, that there is that agreement in all thoſe Princes united againſt <hi>France:</hi> And ſhould not <hi>England</hi> aſſiſt the reſt of the Allies, they would ſoon be over-run by <hi>France;</hi> and ſhould <hi>Holland</hi> be under that Government, <hi>England</hi> could not hold out very long; for when the Marine Forces in <hi>Holland</hi> is united to <hi>France,</hi> we may then rationally conclude, that not only <hi>England,</hi> but the two Neutral, Northern Crowns and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> muſt at length receive Laws from <hi>France;</hi> I will not undertake, that his Holineſs at <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be exempt from his Juriſdiction. I might enlarge upon ſuch reaſons as may be convincing, if it were neceſſary, but it would be ſuperfluous, matters of fact having been ſo much before-hand of that nature, how the <hi>French</hi> Monarch hath treated all perſons that endeavour to thwart his Ambition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that it is our real Intereſt to aſſiſt the reſt of the Confederates, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the preſent inconveniences, and evil conſequents that do attend us, which in a little time may be avoided.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48293:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It is not now a thing Diſputable, for we have too evident Experience, and the Nation has been convinced, that the Growth of <hi>France</hi> would be the Ruine of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> as witneſs thoſe many Parliamentary Addreſſes made to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, as well as by the many Bills brought in, and Acts paſt in the Reign of His preſent Majeſty; and he expoſing his Royal Perſon in order to bring down that lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince, and ſhall we now by a few falſe friends, and their ſly inſinuations, be prevail'd upon to alter our minds, and take thoſe methods that moſt directly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine us. As for Example, ſhould I pretend to go for <hi>Exon</hi> or <hi>Berwick,</hi> we know <hi>Ware</hi> is the Rode to one, and <hi>Hounſlow</hi> to the other, and ſhould be met at <hi>Graveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, Rocheſter, &amp;c.</hi> and purſue that direct Rode by Land and Water, any body that knows the Rode, muſt conclude, I deſign'd for <hi>France,</hi> let my pretences be never ſo much to the contrary.</p>
            <p>It's grievous to think, that when <hi>England</hi> is honoured with the greateſt Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of any Nation under Heaven; and that it will be allowed, its Laws (as to the main of them) exceeding other Nations, but moſt backward as to execution, that which is wanting, is one general Law to put others in execution.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry I have the occaſion to mention a particular caſe that paſt in my own ſight the laſt Year, <hi>viz.</hi> When ſome Overtures were made to ſettle a Trade be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us and the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and diſcourſing with a great Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man concern'd in that Affair, gave me the ſight of the Agent, who was then to go on this Affair, being a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> I asked him, whether ſince the Trade to be promoted, was for <hi>England,</hi> it would not be more proper to ſend an <hi>Engliſhman?</hi> To which he anſwered, <hi>No, for we were too ſluggiſh to promote, even our own real good;</hi> had I not too much experience of the truth of his Anſwer, I ſhould have argued with him; for I have generally obſerved the diſpoſition of too too many guilty of this fault, and more particularly noted by another Pen <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>We have been more careful to receive the Law from <hi>France,</hi> in all their Modes, both in Eating and Wearing, than from the great Creator for our Converſation; and ſo prevalent is the humour of that Country, with us, and ſo powerful the Aſcendant it hath over us, that we ſeem to be <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> only we live in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo that they have ſufficiently revenged themſelves upon us, by the looſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners they have brought among us; but I muſt needs ſay to their Credit, they keep their Wits in their Debaucheries, whilſt we, by over-doing them in the imitation of them, loſe both; What is become of that Antient Education of the Kingdom, our Integrity, Gravity and Manhood, which gave our Nation ſo great Reputation in the World; is it not turned into Swearing and Drinking, a Duel and a Wench? their Prophaneneſs is their Wit; and their baſe Crafts muſt be called Policy; and as this we have learned from <hi>France,</hi> as to our Men, ſo let us conſider as to our Women; but where is that retired Breeding, which made our Women ſo famous for Virtue as they were always for their Beauty; Alas! there hath been a ſort of induſtry uſed to ſubdue their native Modeſty; as if it were an indecent thing to have it, and Arts practiſed to make them hardy againſt their own bluſhes, and maſter their ſhy and baſhful diſpoſition (ſo peculiar to Chaſtity) into an unconcerned Confidence; as if it were their Perfection, to be inſenſible of any ill, and to be tam'd at all things. Strange! that ſobriety ſhould be turned into levity, and luſt call'd love, and wantonneſs good humour; this have been the effect of the French Modes given us.</q> And the ſame Author pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48293:10"/>in the Deſcription of a well-conſtitued Monarchy in ancient Times, with the Miſchiefs that befel them when they grew ſlotful, and gave themſelves to Pride, Luxury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which I crave leave to mention only for a Warning for us to conſider of, his words are theſe, 
<q>The firſt Empire had <hi>Nimrod's</hi> ſtrength, and the Wiſdom of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> to eſtabliſh it; and whilſt <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>ſobriety</hi> laſted, they proſpered, no ſooner came <hi>Voluptuouſneſs</hi> than the Empire decayed; and was at laſt by the baſe <hi>Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacies</hi> of <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> (in whom that Race ended) transfer'd to another family. It was the Policy of an <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> King, to ſubdue the ſtrength of <hi>Babylon</hi> (then under good Diſcipline) not to Invade it with <hi>Force,</hi> but to <hi>Debauch it:</hi> Wherefore he ſent in <hi>Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Muſitians, Cooks, Harlots,</hi> &amp;c. and by thoſe means introducing <hi>Corruption of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> there was little more to do than to take it. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> by his Virtue and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, ſeen in the Siege of <hi>Tyre,</hi> and of many great Enterprizes, recovered and enlarged it to a mighty Empire; and his Diſcipline was ſo excellent (thoſe times conſidered) that it was praiſed in Scripture; but when he grew <hi>Proud</hi> and <hi>Fooliſh,</hi> for getting that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> that had ſhewn it ſelf ſo kind to him, he became a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and grazed among the Beaſts, till God, whom he had forgotten, had reſtored him the heart of a Man and his Throne together.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh we may take up in time, and obſerve how it was brought in amongſt us; for when the two late Kings (to whom not only <hi>England,</hi> but great part of <hi>Europe,</hi> may attribute the preſent War) that during their abode in <hi>France,</hi> a foundation was laid for the ruine of <hi>England,</hi> which was gradually put in execution, as it would bear, and it had certainly been effected, had not the Revolution prevented. It is very pertinent, what is written by another hand on the obſervation of the 29th of <hi>May,</hi> the Birth-day and Reſtoration of <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>Now let us ſee how great cauſe we had to fall into ſo high and exceeding demonſtration of joy; let the event ſhew, how great a Bleſſing this Reſtoration proved to the Nation. We know ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>God gives Kings in his Anger, and takes them away in his Wrath.</hi> Plague, War and Fire came in with King <hi>Charles,</hi> but all little enough, in compariſon of that Floud of Vice and Corruption, in the way of Prophaneneſs, Impiety, Debauchery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which being encouraged by Example and Impunity, followed him, and like a mighty ſtream, have ſo overflowed the Nation, that in all likelihood, it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more Judgments, and many years to come, to purge the Land of it; 'tis over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread almoſt, from the Child in the Cradle, to the Old Man going to his Grave. <hi>Whoredom and Wine take away the heart,</hi> and our Underſtanding too, which make us grow an Effeminate Nation, contemptible to our Neighbours; and made us caſt away the Honour and Intereſt of the Country, and become Tools of the Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Greatneſs of thoſe, whoſe growing Power we ought to have oppoſed; and which ſince, made <hi>Europe</hi> groan, and labour to be delivered from that Bondage or Danger we helped to bring it under: We ſlighted the ſuits and offers of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Princes and States, and Addreſſes of Parliament, who offered their Lives and Fortunes to ſtop the growing Power of <hi>France,</hi> which had her Emiſſaries of both Sexes in our Boſom; by whoſe counſels Parliaments were Adjourned, Prorogued and Diſſolved, whilſt in leſs than 2 Years time above 100000 ſouls, for Religion ſake, forſook the Kingdom, inſomuch that one perſon, <hi>viz. Tilham,</hi> carried 3000 unto the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> upon the account of Religion; and carried great part of our Trade; and that which is remarkable is, that we laid the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48293:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>foundation of the loſing it, at leaſt a great part of it, the ſame way we got it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But this was what was all along deſign'd in both our late Reigns, and without doubt agreed unto by the <hi>French</hi> King, when thoſe Princes were ſo long in <hi>France,</hi> which is plainly proved, and more enlarged by other Pens.</p>
            <p>Were the conſequences of theſe things well conſidered, which is matter of fact, and were we more (as true <hi>Engliſhmen</hi>) unanimous (and abate thoſe little peaks of no true value) and not ſuffer our ſelves to be impoſed upon, we need not fear the moſt daring and potent Adverſary whatſoever; but on the contrary, if we ſhould be led away by Jealouſie and Diſcontent, and thereby give way to our Enemies, what confuſion may not be expected? eſpecially among the common Peogle (who hath hitherto, by almoſt a Miracle, been reſtrained by the Lord, who <hi>ſtilleth the noiſe or tumult of the People</hi>) for they, if let looſe, not walking by Law, Rule or Reaſon, but through Raſhneſs and Madneſs run themſelves, and the Nation into great Confuſion and Miſery.</p>
            <p>And as the caſe ſtands at preſent, we cannot expect to enjoy the Liberty and Peace at home, without great coſt to keep the War at a diſtance. I would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore offer ſome Conſiderations in reference to thoſe unavoidable Taxes, that tho they may be great, and hard to be born, eſpecially by ſome ſort of perſons, yet if we conſider it's for the preſervation of our future ſecurity and eaſe, as well as of, our lives, and the comfortable uſe of what is left.</p>
            <p>And if perſons, tho no preſent Diſtemper be upon them, are voluntary under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking a Courſe of Phyſick, and are expoſed to no little pain and trouble in its working, yet they bear it patiently, becauſe they expect the effects thereof, both for the preſerving their preſent Health, and preventing future diſtempers.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to add, that tho the War is very uneaſie to many, yet I may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay, and that upon good grounds, that had not the ſaid War fell out as it did, it's more than probable, that we ſhould e'r this time, have loſt the greateſt part of our Trade by <hi>France.</hi> And I am happily prevented in dilating my thoughts further on this Subject, by the remembrance of my old Acquaintance, the ingenious and faithful Monitor, Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvel,</hi> who, tho dead many years ſince, yet as if he had beheld our preſent circumſtances, expreſſed himſelf in theſe words in the year 1677. <hi>A more evident and certain reaſon of our decay in Trade, and the grand ſpring of this whole matter, lies in</hi> France; <hi>that King is a moſt vigilant and potent Prince, for he hath made War with all</hi> Europe, <hi>with his Sword againſt his Enemies, but againſt his Friends by Traffick, which is indeed, as the more juſt, ſo the more effectual way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying them; but among all, none hath on this latter account more ſuffered than</hi> England; <hi>for beſides the Wine, which we purchaſe at moſt exceſſive rates, and for the moſt part for ready money; and beſides theſe Trinkets, of which we are ſo fond, and to the making of which the</hi> French <hi>Genius was formerly adopted; he hath for many years applied his People to the making ſolid Trades of Cloth and Stuffs (made of our Wool) and indeed of all things valuable, embracing in effect, or in projection, the</hi> Univerſal Monarchy of Commerce. <hi>Never did any Prince ſo addict himſelf wholly to the encouragement of Trade and Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; to this he hath either wholly prohibited, or which is</hi> tanto mount, <hi>laid ſo exceſſive Impoſitions upon all our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Manufacture, that they are in a manner totally excluded, and we have no Commodity to exchange with, but whatever we have of his, muſt be bought
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48293:11"/>with a Penny; inſomuch that I have a particular, drawn up in Parliament, wherein they have computed, beſides the</hi> lucrum ceſſorum, <hi>that the Nation ſuſtained a clear loſs of eleven hundred thouſand Pounds yearly by the</hi> French <hi>Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He further ſaith, <hi>The</hi> French, <hi>who were not long ſince, but the</hi> Milliners <hi>of</hi> Europe, <hi>are now become, or pretend to be the Cape Merchants; and that King gives not only the Mode, but Garment to all</hi> Chriſtendome, <hi>and the World puts it ſelf into his Livery at their own expence. Well may we therefore complain of the death rather than deadneſs of our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture, when from this cauſe it receives ſuch an obſtruction, even to ſuffocation; when we are not only deprived of that general and gainful vent that we had formerly in</hi> France <hi>it ſelf: but in all other places where we Traffick, we meet the</hi> French <hi>at every Town, and the Foreign Poſt brings News from all Parts, that they come before us, and have underſold us in the ſame Commodity; and to this Diſeaſe which is ſo mortal, and which is beyond any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man to remedy, we do more particularly contribute by thoſe vaſt quantities of Wool which are Tranſported to</hi> France, <hi>ſo that</hi> Callice <hi>is ſtill no leſs our Staple than when it was under the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Dominion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it was thus ſo long ago, we may by woful experience, conclude the <hi>French</hi> had grown much more great in ſo many years after.</p>
            <p>Give me leave a little to reflect upon what paſt in the 2 laſt Reigns, both as to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo Diſſenters, of which the Nation conſiſts. Firſt, As to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Diſſenters, when they were violently perſecuted in the later end of the Reign of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and beginning of King <hi>James,</hi> what would that ſort of People have done to have purchaſed the Liberty now enjoyed?</p>
            <p>Secondly, And thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> not only of the Clergy, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Laity, both Nobility and Gentry, as well as Tradeſmen, what would they have parted with to be ſecured of their Properties, when envaded, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were Tryed? Yea, ſome of our <hi>Engliſh Catholicks</hi> themſelves, that were think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men, ſome of which I could name, when the <hi>Iriſh</hi> was for burning; and as all knows what ſort of People they are, making no difference wherever they come, even in <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, amongſt thoſe of their own pretended Religion, if it may be called a Religion.</p>
            <p>As to our preſent Taxes, let us compare the ſtate of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> come, and where the Seat of War is, who are forced not only to pay Taxes to both Parties, but at laſt, all and their Lives to boot.</p>
            <p>If we on the other hand, conſider the value of Freedom and Trade, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>Holland,</hi> who at all times, both in time of Peace as well as War, bear great Taxes, yet their Freedom and Trade make them go through it, as if none at all; and we our ſelves at this day, tho ſome particular perſons may be great ſufferers, yet the <hi>body of the Nation,</hi> for many years laſt paſt, never lived ſo great as now, if we may judge by outward appearance; and give me leave to ſay, had we no Taxes, and ſhould loſe our Trade, as before hinted, we ſhould be miſerable, for it's that which is the main Spring and Fountain that gives life unto, and doth ſupport a People or Nation, and the want of which at preſent in the Bowels of <hi>France,</hi> doth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expoſe that People.</p>
            <p>I ſay again, when I conſider the many Millions this Nation hath contributed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the War, the great loſſes many of our Merchants have ſuſtained, as alſo the general Dammage by the abuſe of our Coin; notwithſtanding all theſe things, if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48293:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>we look through the Nation in general, (excepting ſome few perſons in particular) where is the juſt complaint? where are the Countries, Citys or Towns, that doth viſibly demonſtrate their Poverty? where are Tables leſs furniſhed? where are the Backs or Heads of each Sex not ornamented? Let us therefore not befool our ſelves, and court Poverty and Ruine to our ſelves? for can it otherwiſe be expected, that if ever the late King ſhould be ſettled here, he muſt of neceſſity be the <hi>French</hi> King's Deputy; and ſuppoſing we may eſcape the Sword of the <hi>French</hi> King's Forces, its eaſie to apprehend what our condition will be hereafter, if we look back and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how the <hi>French</hi> incroached upon us in our Trade in the laſt Two Reigns, while we had Peace with them, that for near 20 years together, the over-ballance of the Trade with <hi>France,</hi> was near 4 Millions <hi>per Annum,</hi> we cannot in reaſon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that our loſs will be leſs for the future, when we are but a Province of <hi>France;</hi> and then let us conſider, what our condition will be (if we eſcape with our lives, which will be difficult) when we ſhall loſe our Trade and Freedom, and be liable to make good to <hi>France,</hi> all the Debts the late King hath contracted with the <hi>French</hi> ſince his Abdication (as <hi>Spain</hi> hath been, for the Money borrowed to make War with Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) for can it be ever thought by any conſidering perſon, that the great and extraordinary Charge the <hi>French</hi> King hath been put to, both in the Defence of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſo long, and all the coſt in <hi>France,</hi> together with all the Preparations in the year 1692, and this late intended Invaſion; as alſo the Debts contracted in <hi>France</hi> ever ſince the ſaid Abdication, muſt not be allowed him; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the gratifying his Friends; let us therefore conſider all theſe things together, and expoſtulate with our ſelves, what ſtate and condition we ſhall then be in? for my part I dread to ſpeak or write.</p>
            <p>But ſhould Peace be made up before he is brought ſo low, as not to be in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to hurt us, the conſequence would be very bad; for 'tis plain, that there is nothing but what we have reaſon to fear, if <hi>France</hi> gets advantageouſly out of this War; and that after the Proof they have had of their Forces, they will treat their Neighbours hereafter with much more ſtate than they have already done.</p>
            <p>This is certain, they have done things which they could ſcarce think themſelves capable of doing, and therefore we have more reaſon to be jealous of that King than ever, and ſhould make uſe of the <hi>preſent League</hi> to reduce them into their juſt bounds. Experience has but too plainly convinced us, That there was need of no leſs than all the Powers that are united in the preſent War, to make head againſt <hi>France.</hi> But who can aſſure us, that it ſhall be poſſible to unite them a ſecond time? Can ſo many circumſtances that meet together to give birth to the League, concur afreſh to form a new one? Every one knows, that to produce and confirm this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was neceſſary that all the Allies were convinced of the Injuſtice of the <hi>French</hi> Proceedings; that every one of them in particular had experienced their unhappy effects; and that one common danger had put them into an indiſpenſible neceſſity of defending themſelves; and how many incidents have occurred ſince? The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of King <hi>James;</hi> the happy Revolution that followed it, and the Reduction of <hi>Ireland,</hi> have been degrees by which the Nation has been put in a ſtate to act with vigour againſt the common Enemy.</p>
            <p>It was not enough to be Governed by a Prince that would not be diſcouraged by difficulties, nor diſturbed by dangers, who Commands his Armies in Perſon, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48293:12"/>animates them by his Example: The State of Affairs required; beſides this, that this Prince ſhould have Credit in <hi>Germany,</hi> to oppoſe, with ſucceſs, the Intrigues of <hi>France</hi> there; and that he ſhould be at the Head of the Forces of a powerful Republick, both by Sea and Land; and ſure there need no great pains to prove, That ſince we cannot promiſe our ſelves a like Juncture hereafter, 'tis abſolutely neceſſary, to make the beſt uſe of it while we have it.</p>
            <p>'Tis eaſie to foreſee, That ſome years of Repoſe, would give <hi>France</hi> the means of making a ſtronger Party in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Northern Courts;</hi> ſo that it would not fail to make uſe of the firſt Revolution that ſhould happen in <hi>Europe,</hi> to renew the War. No body is ignorant, that 'tis their Policy not to diſarm in time of Peace; and that the Revenue of that Crown is always the ſame, which gives it infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite advantage, when it Attacks thoſe who are uſed to disband at the end of a War; and which keep up the Armies by Taxes, which are preſently intercepted by Peace. Beſides this, the <hi>French</hi> King is abſolute in his Government; his Frontier Towns are extreamly ſtrong; and in ſuch a ſcituation as to command all the Neighbouring Countries; ſo that he is always ready to make Invaſions, and out of danger of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them made on him; and the <hi>unquiet Genius</hi> of that Nation, together with the care that is taken to form it to <hi>Slavery,</hi> requires frequent Wars abroad.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that Crown is ſo far from having the Hopes and the Repoſe of its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in view, that its main ſtudy is to keep them low. The Clergy can no more vaunt of any Prerogative; the King is as abſolute over the Spiritualty, as he is over the Temporality: All depends upon his good Pleaſure, which is now become the only Law of the State. The Nobility have loſt all their Priviledges; they are reduced to a neceſſity of cringing ſeverely to an <hi>Intendant</hi> of a Province; and have no other way to aſpire to any diſtinction, but by low and unbecoming ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>As to the Subſidies granted to our King, it is to be conſidered, tho they are great, yet he himſelf doth not diſpoſe them for his private advantage; but they are made uſe of for our own ſafety, the King adventuring the hazard of his own Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in purſuance of the end deſign'd in all the Taxes, <hi>That theſe Nations might be Settled, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore, take heed Oh Murmurers! leſt God deal with you as with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s time, when that People had ſuch Experiences of the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God by his many Deliverances by his own Hand, and by the Perſons he was pleaſed to raiſe as his Inſtruments; but (too much like unto you) this was not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory unto them, but they would chooſe a King, and declined the method which God had been pleaſed to lead them by; but require of <hi>Samuel</hi> a King to Judge them, like other Nations, and the Lord permitted <hi>Samuel</hi> to anſwer their deſire, ſaying, that they had not rejected him, <hi>viz. Samuel,</hi> but had rejected the Lord, according to all the Works they had done, <hi>viz</hi> the Murmurers (for there were always ſome that ſtood in the Gap) ſince the day they came out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> And when they were to be gratified, <hi>Samuel</hi> was ordered by the Lord, to ſhew them the manner of their King, <hi>(viz.) This ſhall be the manner of the King that ſhall Reign over you, he will take your Sons and Daughters for Himſelf, and he will take your Fields and your Vineyards, and give them to his Servants: and ye ſhall cry out in that day becauſe of your King, which you ſhall have choſen you, and the Lord will not hear
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48293:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>you in that day; nevertheleſs the People refuſed to obey the Voice of</hi> Samuel; <hi>and they ſaid, Nay, but we will have a King over us,</hi> &amp;c. How plainly applicable this would be to our caſe, is eaſie to underſtand, ſhould we by our Murmurings, provoke the Lord to anger againſt us; and by our Diviſions and Animoſities one againſt the other, intice and animate the <hi>French</hi> King to attempt another Invaſion, under the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pretences of a Magnanimous and Royal Act of Reſtoring King <hi>James</hi> to his Throne again: But alas! who can deſcribe the conſequence of ſuch an Act, I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to go about it; and Methinks! the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> yoke under their King is eaſie to what we may expect: To begin with the firſt clauſe, <hi>He will take your Sons and your Daughters for Himſelf,</hi> denoting the abſolute Authority the King was to have over their Children, for the placing of them here or there, this or that Employment, as is there expreſs'd, noble and ignoble, ſome were to be Captains of Thouſands, others of Fifties; Confectioners, Bakers; ſome to reap, ſome to ſow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as you may read in the Story: Here is Mercy mix'd with Judgment, an ordinary variety of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of humane Life, wherein no Man, even the meaneſt ſervant, was to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barr'd the placid reflection (he having done his duty) upon the Law of God, <hi>Fear God, Honour the King,</hi> the meaneſt <hi>Iſraelite</hi> reaping, might rejoice in his happy ſtate, compar'd with <hi>Egypt's</hi> cruel, oppreſſive Slavery. But oh fearful Thought! What can we expect from our Enemies, who, I am bold to affirm, are the Enemies of God and good Men? Stupid Souls! Can you think the <hi>French</hi> King will be kinder to you than to his own, Faithful, Loyal Subjects, who gain'd him the Crown by their indefatigable Labour and true Valour: Take a view of his Gratitude and their Recompence; Are they made Captains of Thouſands and Hundreds; yea, tell me where is the poor <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Reaper allow'd to dwell peaceably in all his Dominions? Inſtead of taking their Sons and Daughters to himſelf, ſome he hath ſent to the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Slavery of the Gallies; ſome he has deſtroy'd without Mercy, in moſt inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Tragical manner; and, are not our eyes daily beholders of the many, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly baniſh'd Subjects of that King, beſides the innumerable multitudes, baniſh'd other Countries? Will your Sons and Daughters, think ye, be better uſed? No no, be not deceived, the Fire of his Ambition, Hatred, Covetouſneſs, is rather ſeven times hotter; and inſtead of Delighting in the Flames of <hi>London</hi>'s Houſes, he would be glad to ſee (<hi>Nero</hi> like) your Sons and Daughters, (how delicate ſoever they are in your eyes) burnt with them.</p>
            <p>And to the ſecond deſcription of the murmuring <hi>Iſraelites</hi> King, <hi>And he will take your Fields and your Vineyards, and give them to his Servants, &amp;c.</hi> Here the King's peremptory will over his Subjects Eſtates is deſcribed; an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> with an <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite;</hi> one advanced, and the other brought low; no Family exempted from ſuch viciſſitudes; but the moſt dejected <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> tho never ſo abject in the King's ſight, if free from blemiſhes of the Law, might have recourſe to the Temple, and there rejoice in the God of his Father <hi>Abraham:</hi> Bleſſed Priviledge, meliorating the ſowr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt affliction. But what? Oh murmuring <hi>Engliſhman!</hi> Canſt thou expect from the <hi>French</hi> King, that great Deſtroyer of Countrys, Vineyards, Corn-Fields, Paſtorage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Do you Think, if you eſcape with your Lives, you ſhall diſpoſe of your Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Riches, Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Vain thought! Forget not how you have been ſerved by your own Kings, born among you, who never arriv'd to ſo infinite Barbarity as he hath done; yet have not they baniſh'd ſeveral of your fellow Subjects to the <hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies?</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48293:13"/>diſpos'd your Goods and Money amongſt vile Informers. Is <hi>France</hi> more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hearted? What bravely erected Churches, curious Manſions, fair Eſtates of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects hath he demoliſhed and made heaps of Rubbiſh, even Dunghils of; and forced the Owners of them into other Countries, to ſeek for places of Refuge, where they might ſigh out their piteous complaints, like the bleſs'd Souls under the Altar, <hi>How long, O Lord, juſt and true, &amp;c.?</hi> And will he be kinder to you, ye hard-hearted Murmurers? No! He will eſteem the meaneſt pitiful, flattering <hi>Vale de Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre-Monſieur,</hi> before the moſt noble, generous-hearted Peer of <hi>England,</hi> and make him poſſeſſor of his Eſtate. Pray tell me, have ye not ſeen from among your ſelves, a cunning, tricking, flattering perſon, to ſerve the Prince's by-ends, preferr'd before you? What! expect ye kinder uſage from <hi>France?</hi> Don't miſtake, if ye by your Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings provoke the Lord to Anger, and your hatred one of another, break his commands, and bring the <hi>French</hi> among you, The Dogs of his Flock will he make to traverſe your Eſtates, and when he has done, if it were poſſible, make them Heirs of them, rather than you. His Revenge is not a light matter. Provoke not the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to let it out upon you.</p>
            <p>It may not be impertinent to re-mind you, the greateſt Grievance you at preſent lie under, in reference to the Coin, is from the pre-meditated revenge, cunning intrigues of your Antient Enemies the <hi>French,</hi> it being part of the Plot in 1678; as may be ſeen in the Narrative of the Plot, and in a late Diſcourſe, called <hi>A Tragedy, &amp;c.</hi> in theſe words— <hi>This Flot was to be effected by</hi> worſe than <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Intereſt; Tranſportation of Trade, People, Stock and Money, AD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTERATING MONEY AND PLATE. To which end they have Bankers, Merchants, Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths and other Traders, whom they ſtock and ſet up with Money of their Society; of which they boaſt to have one hundred thouſand pounds Caſh,</hi> &amp;c. What Stock they may have now, is inconceivably great. Oh <hi>England!</hi> how long will you nouriſh theſe poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Vipers of the World, by your Murmurings and Jealouſies, and diſcern it not?</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude in the words of another, <hi>As the Caſe ſtands now, there are but two Ways, Victory or Slavery; We muſt either make the</hi> French <hi>ſtoop to us, or be forced to ſubmit to them; there remains no Terms of Peace for us, but what will fix an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infamy upon the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Name: In ſhort, the Greatneſs of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> France <hi>is incompatible, if they riſe, we muſt fall; and the richer they grow, the poorer we ſhall be; their Glory will be erected on our Shame; and a Peace at this time would introduce far greater, and more certain Calamities than War,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Awake</hi> England! <hi>Thine Enemies are not only</hi> upon thee, <hi>but</hi> within thee.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48293:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
